<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The iudgement of the Godly and learned father M. Henry Bullinger chiefe preacher and pastor of the Church of Zurich in Swicerlande, declaring it to be lawfull for the ministers of the Churche of Englande, to weare the apparell prescribed by the lawes and orders of the same realme.</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111156</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846563</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846563</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17189)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 198:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The iudgement of the Godly and learned father M. Henry Bullinger chiefe preacher and pastor of the Church of Zurich in Swicerlande, declaring it to be lawfull for the ministers of the Churche of Englande, to weare the apparell prescribed by the lawes and orders of the same realme.</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By William Seres, dwelling in Paules Church yarde, at the signe of the hedgehogge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1566]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from 2nd colophon.</note>
                  <note>In English and Latin.</note>
                  <note>In two parts; 2nd part has separate register.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 has caption title: Reuerendis in Christo patribus D. Roberto Horno Winton .. .</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi⁴ A-C⁴ D²  [2nd] A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 4064 (Part 1) and also STC 4075 (Part 2).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Iudgement of the</hi> Godly and learned <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, M. Henry</hi> Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger chiefe Preacher <hi>and Paſtor of the Church</hi> of Zurich in <hi>Swicer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, declaring it to be</hi> lawfull for the <hi>Miniſters of</hi> the Church of Englande, to weare the <hi>Apparell preſcribed by the Lawes</hi> and orders of the ſame Realme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> at London by William <hi>Seres, dwelling in Paules Church</hi> yarde, at the ſigne of the <hi>Hedgehogge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:2"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EING THAT Maiſter Bullinger himſelfe of ſpecial good wil and zeale towards the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Englande, and the Miniſters of the ſame, hauing trauayled, and taken payne to write his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in this matter, thought it expedient to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate the ſame, not onely with thoſe two brethren here, at whoſe requeſt he wrote his minde herein: But alſo with certaine Byſhops of this Realme, as by his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to them directed and herevnto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, apeareth: &amp; that for the peace &amp; quietneſſe of this Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, as he himſelfe affirmeth: And conſidering alſo, that the iudgement of two notable learned men, Maiſter D. Bucer, and maiſter D. Peter Martyr touching this controuerſie, hath alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy bene ſet forth and publiſhed, It is
<pb facs="tcp:11542:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> therefore thought good alſo to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh in print the ſayde iudgement of Maiſter Bullinger, being a man ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly well learned and Godly, and a worthy Miniſter in Chriſtes Church, not doubting but that muche good ſhall inſue thereof, both to the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of weake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences troubled about this matter, and alſo to the ſatiſfaction of thoſe which without contention or affection ſeeke only the truth of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine in this behalfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Reuerende</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Chriſt, D. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Horne B. of Wincheſter,</hi> D. Grindall B. of London, <hi>D. Parkhurst B. of Norwitch</hi> in England. &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Euerende Fathers, Honorable, &amp; dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued brethren. The Lord Ieſus bleſſe you, and kepe you from al euil. We ſend you the copie of our writing concerning the mater of Apparell, ſent by vs to N. &amp; M. men learned and godly, our worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful brethren. And therfore ſend we it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that ye maye vnderſtande, howe that we deale not priuately with your brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without the knowledge of you, which are the principall Miniſters, and that we to the vttermoſt of our powers doe ſéeke the peace and quietneſſe of your Churches in all things. And we praye the Lord alwayes to ſaue the ſtate there, and kéepe you in concorde. We alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte you our right Reuerende, and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb facs="tcp:11542:4"/> brethren, to haue good regarde vnto faythfull Miniſters, and learned men: for ſuch alſo commonly haue their affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Wherfore the Apoſtle alſo war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men to beare one an others burthen. Ye by your authority may do much with the moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Princeſſe your Quene, entreate ye hir Maieſtie, that the good brethren may be reconciled and reſtored. And we praye you honorable, and deare brother M. Horne to whome theſe letters may be firſt deliuered, that ye will cauſe them forthwith to be caryed to the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Norwich, and ſo communicate them with M. Iewell, M. Sandes, and M. Pilkington, to whom by Gods grace I meane to write the nexte Frankford mart. Theſe letters I wrote in all haſte aſwell in myne owne as in <hi>Gualters</hi> name, and ſent them to <hi>Baſile,</hi> thence to be conueighed to <hi>Andwerpe.</hi> We praye you hartily to ſignifie whether ye haue receiued them. Fare ye wel right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend. The Lord bleſſe you &amp; your labors.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>At <hi>Zurich</hi> 
                        <date>the thirde of Maij. 1566.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your Bullinger.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:4"/>
                  <head>¶ The Copie of Maſter <hi>Bullingers Letter <hi>to N. and M.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhypfull and welbeloued brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lorde Ieſus bleſſe you, and kepe you from all euill. I haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your Letters, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I perceiued you N. to complaine, that mine anſwere made to your queſtion ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ouer ſhort. Albeit I good Brother, then ſaw no cauſe, neyther now do, why I ſhuld write any long letters. For ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired onely my iudgement concerning the matter of Apparell, where aboute there was contention in Englande. To that queſtion I thought good to anſwere you briefly. For I coulde well in fewe wordes declare my minde. Furthermore I knewe that <hi>D. Peter Martyr</hi> of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memorie, had often &amp; at large hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſame queſtion both at Oxeforde and here with vs, wherevnto I had not
<pb facs="tcp:11542:5"/> what to adde. And I remember that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was then made of my minde alſo, in the letter which I wrote to you Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther M. And againe to ſay what I think in a worde or two, I can neuer allow it, if ye be commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to execute your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie at an Aultar, burthened rather than garniſhed with the Image of the Crucifixe, and in a Maſſing garment, that is, in an Albe and Veſtment bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring on the backe alſo the Image of the Crucifixe. But as farre as I can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue by Letters brought oute of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, there is now no contention for ſuch apparell. But the queſtion is, whether it be lawfull for the miniſters of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to weare a rounde or ſquare cappe, and the whyte Veſture whiche they call a Surpleſſe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wearing wherof your Miniſters maye be diſcerned from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? And whether they ought to forſake the miniſterie, and their ſacred place, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than weare ſuch apparell? To this queſtion, I anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right Reuerende <hi>D. Robert Horne</hi> Biſhoppe of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter the laſt Mart, and that briefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating
<pb facs="tcp:11542:5"/> the wordes of <hi>D. Martyr.</hi> To him had my fellow Miniſter, and deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued Alliance <hi>Rodolph Gualter</hi> written a little afore, the copie of whoſe letters I ſend to you, and our other bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, incloſed in theſe. Therefore if ye wil heare vs, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye require our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning the matter of Apparel, as in your laſte letters ye ſignified vnto me, beholde, ye haue in that Epiſtle our iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whervnto if ye can not agree, we truely are moſt hartily ſorie, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no further counſell, we doe hartily and without ceaſing pray vnto the Lord whom we muſt in all things &amp; alwayes haue reſpect vnto, that he with his grace and might wil eaſe the preſent troubles.</p>
                  <p>You brother N. haue propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine queſtions, and our brother M. hath gathered moe of the ſame argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And albeit I according to my ſimple rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe neuer liked to haue maters drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into ſo many queſtions, and intangled in intricate doubtes, whiche otherwiſe being of themſelues more ſimple, might in fewe wordes and plainely ynough be
<pb facs="tcp:11542:6"/> anſwered: yet wil I note ſomewhat vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euerye one, that I maye herein alſo gratifie you my worſhipfull and moſte dearely beloued brethren, as farre forth as my poore ſkill and abilitie will giue me leaue. And I beſéeche you to receyue theſe of me your brother and harty louer in good parte, and iudge of them with a quiet minde and frée from all affections. I vtterlye abhorre contentions, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doe I more humblie craue at the Lordes hande, than that he will remoue farre from the Churche all contentions, which from the beginning and alwayes haue greatly annoyed true Godlineſſe, and rent a ſunder the Churche when it was reaſonablie quiet and in good caſe.</p>
                  <p>Where ye aſke, whether lawes of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell ought to be preſcribed to Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall perſons, that thereby they may be diſcerned from laye men? I anſwere that there is doubtfulneſſe in the worde <hi>Ought,</hi> for if it be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for neceſſarie, &amp; pertayning to the obteyning of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I do not think the law makers them
<pb facs="tcp:11542:6"/> ſelues to be of this minde. But if it be meant, that this may be done for come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and beautie, or eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to be a certaine ciuill obſeruance, or ſome ſuche thing be vnderſtoode, as that is that the Apoſtle would haue a church Miniſter or Biſhop to be <hi>Coſmion,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is comely, I ſée not what he offendeth that vſeth ſuch Apparell, or that commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to vſe ſuch.</p>
                  <p>Whether the Ceremoniall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce of the Leuitical Prieſthoode be to be called againe into the Church? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, If a cappe and garment not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comelye for a Miniſter, and voyde of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, be commaunded to be vſed of Miniſters, no man verely can truelye ſaye, that Iudaiſme is reſtored. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore I repeate here that I ſée <hi>D. Martyr</hi> to haue anſwered to this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who when he had ſhewed that the Sacramentes of the olde Lawe are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, which may not be brought again into the Church of Chriſt hauing bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and the holye Supper, he added: There were neuertheleſſe in the Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb facs="tcp:11542:7"/> lawe certaine actions of ſuch ſort, as they coulde not properly be called ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for they ſerued for comelyneſſe and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious vſe, which things as agréeable to the light of nature, and helping ſomewhat to our commoditie, I iudge may both be reſtored and retained. Who ſéeth not that the Apoſtles for the peace and better agréement of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded the Gentiles to abſtaine from bloud &amp; ſtrangled? Theſe things without controuerſie were legall and Leuiticall. And none of vs is ignorant that Tithes alſo are at this day in many places appointed to finde the Miniſters. It is manifeſt that Pſalmes &amp; Hymnes are ſong in the Church, which thinges yet the Leuites alſo vſed. And not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this, we haue holy dayes in memory of the Lordes reſurrection, and others. Nowe ſhall all theſe be done away bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be monuments of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old law? ye ſée then that all the Leuiticals are not ſo abrogate, but that ſome of them may ſtill be vſed. Thus much he.</p>
                  <p>Whether it be lawefull to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate
<pb facs="tcp:11542:7"/> with the Papiſtes in apparell? I anſwere. It is not yet proued that the Pope brought difference of apparell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church. Nay, it is certaine that difference of apparell is farre more aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient than the Pope. Neyther doe I ſée why we may not communicate with the Papiſtes, in apparell not ſuperſtitious, but politike and comely. If in nothing we might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with them, then muſt we forſake all Churches, receyue no ſtipends, vſe no baptiſme, reade ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, nor Nicene Créede, yea, and then muſt we away with the Lords Prayer. Neyther doe ye borrow of them any ceremonies. Apparell from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of your reformation was neuer remoued, &amp; is ſtill retayned, not by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe order, but by force of the Princes lawe, as a thing indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and politike. So verely, if ye vſe as a ciuill thing the Cap and diſtinct Apparell, it ſauoureth neither of Iudaiſme, nor Monkerie. For theſe ſéeke to ſéeme ſeparate from ciuill life, and put merite in their peculiar ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite. So <hi>Euſtachius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sebaſtia</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11542:8"/> was conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned, not ſimplie for his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar habite, but for that he put holineſſe in it. The Cannons of the Councell of <hi>Gangra, Laodicea,</hi> and of the ſixt Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node are wel knowen. If ſo be that ſome of the common people be perſuaded, that this ſauoureth of Poperie, Iewiſhneſſe and Monkerie, let them be admoniſhed, and better taught concerning theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And if by the vndiſcrete clamors of ſome, blowen out aboute this matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Common people, many are made vnquiet, lette them that doe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, they pul not heauier burthens vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their owne neckes, and prouoke the Quéenes Maieſtie, &amp; finally bring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye faithfull Miniſters into daunger, whence they ſhall hardelye be able to winde out.</p>
                  <p>Whether ſuche as haue hitherto en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed their libertie, may with ſafe conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence wrappe both them ſelues and the Church in this ſeruitude, by force of the Quéenes Iniunctions? I aunſwere. I thinke beſt to prouide that there be no odious diſputations, clamors, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions
<pb facs="tcp:11542:8"/> about the matter of Apparell, and ſo by ſuche importunitie occaſion be giuen to the Quenes maieſtie no longer to leaue it free for them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hitherto haue vſed their libertie, but being exaſperated with their outcries be in maner forced to commaunde either to receiue the eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Apparell, or giue ouer their rowmes. Surely me think it a ſtraunge thing (I ſpeake it vnder your correction right worſhipfull and welbeloued Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) that ye perſuade your ſelues, that ye may not with ſafe conſcience ſubmitte your ſelues and the Churches to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude of Apparell, and doe not rather weighe, that if ye will not vſe a thing méere pollitike and indifferent but ſtill contende odiouſly, into what a ſeruitude ye then bring both your ſelues and your Churches, by leauing of your rowmes, and ſetting of the Churches wide open vnto Wolues, or at the leſt to more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit Teachers, which are not ſo furniſhed as ye be to inſtruct the people, haue ye then well defended the libertie of the Church, when ye miniſter occaſion to
<pb facs="tcp:11542:9"/> oppreſſe the Church with more and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uier burdens? ye are not ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t what a number ſéeke for, how they be affected towardes the preaching of the Goſpell, what maner of perſons ſhall ſuccéede in your places, and what is to be looked for at their hands.</p>
                  <p>Whether the Apparell of the cleargie be a thing indifferent? Verilie it ſéemeth a thing indifferent, being a ciuill thing, and hauing regarde to comelineſſe, order and beautie, without putting anye Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in it. Thus much briefly I thought to ſay to your queſtions my right well learned and welbeloued Brother N.</p>
                  <p>Nowe I come to the queſtions of our brother M. alſo, in declaration whereof I will paraduenture be ſhorter. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther peculiar Apparell diſtinct from laye men were euer appointed for miniſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church? Whether at this day ſuch ought to be appointed in reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches alſo? I anſwere: That in the olde Churche there was diſtinct Apparell of prieſtes it appeareth by the eccleſiaſticall hiſtorie of <hi>Theodoret lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 27. and
<pb facs="tcp:11542:9"/> 
                     <hi>Socrates lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they vſed <hi>Pallium</hi> in miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, none y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath but ouer ſéene the monumentes of olde wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, can be ignorant. Therefore I ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified afore that diuerſitie of apparel had not his beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope. <hi>Euſebius</hi> at the leaſt recordeth out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient writers, how that Iohn the Apoſtle wore at <hi>Ephaeſus</hi> a Biſhops attire vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his head, terming it: <hi>Pelatum ſeu La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina pontificalis.</hi> As touching ſaint <hi>Ciprian</hi> the holy martyr, <hi>Pontius</hi> the Deacon writeth, that a little before he ſhoulde be beheaded, he gaue vnto him that ſhoulde beheade him, his veſture called <hi>Birrus,</hi> and to his Deacon, his veſture called <hi>Dalmatica,</hi> and ſo ſtoode himſelfe in linnen. Furthermore <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> maketh mention of the whyte veſture of miniſters of the Church. And it is certayne that Chriſtians when they came firſt vnto Chriſtes religion, and to the Church, for a gowne put on a cloke. For which cauſe when they were moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the Gentiles <hi>Tertullian</hi> wrote a very learned treatiſe <hi>de Pallio.</hi> I coulde
<pb facs="tcp:11542:10"/> bring forthe manye other things of this ſorte, if theſe were not ſufficient. In deede I had rather haue nothing layed vpon the miniſters againſt their willes, and that they might vſe the maner of the Apoſtles, but for as much as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quéenes Maieſtie requireth the Cap only and the Surpleſſe, wherein (as is oftentimes ſayde already) ſhe putteth no Religion, and the ſame things haue bene vſed of the auncient Fathers, when the Church was in better caſe, without all ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and fault, I woulde wiſh good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters not to put all the going forward of Religion in theſe things, as if they were all, and ſumme, according to the prouerb, but yelde ſomewhat to the time and not odiouſely to ſtriue about a thing indifferent, but iudge ſoberly that theſe things may be borne, but we muſt goe forwarde with the tyme. For that ſuche are nearer to the ſimplicitie of the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles as knowe no ſuch differences or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them not, &amp; yet in the meane whyle abhorre not diſcipline in Apparell.</p>
                  <p>Whether preſcription of Apparell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeth
<pb facs="tcp:11542:10"/> with chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libertie? I anſwere: That things indifferent admitte ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time preſcription, and enforcement alſo, as I may terme it, as touching the vſe, and not for neceſſitie, ſo as that which is by nature indifferent ſhoulde be thruſt vpon the conſcience as neceſſarie, and ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mindes driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into ſcrupoloſitie. Times verilie, and places of holy aſſemblies, are rightely compted among indifferent things, and yet if theſe then be no ſet or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what confuſion I pray you, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order woulde growe therevpon?</p>
                  <p>Whether any new ceremonies maye be heaped beſide the expreſſe rule of the worde of God? I anſwere, that I lyke not heaping of new ceremonies, and yet I denie not but that ſome may be ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo that the ſeruice of God be not put in them, but appointed for order and diſcipline. Chriſt himſelfe kept the feaſt or ceremonie of the <hi>Encoenia</hi> or dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and yet we finde not this feaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the lawe. To be ſhorte, the greater part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> propoſitions or queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning Apparell, ſtandeth in
<pb facs="tcp:11542:11"/> this, whether lawes for Apparell ought or be lawfull to be made in the Church. And it bringeth the queſtion to a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, to wit, what order may be taken for ceremonies. To theſe propoſitions I anſwere briefely, that I for my parte I had rather haue no ceremonies, but ſuch as are neceſſarie, thruſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church, yet in the meane ſeaſon I graunt, that lawes concerning ceremonies, paradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not very neceſſarie, and ſometime vnprofitable, may not ſtraight waye be condemned of impietie, and ſo troubles and ſchiſmes rayſed in the Church, ſo long as they be voyde of ſuperſtition, and the things are in their owne nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</p>
                  <p>Whether it be lawfull to reſtore the aboliſhed rytes of the Iewes, &amp; to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late ceremonies properly dedicate to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Idolaters, to the vſe of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches? To this queſtion I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere afore, when I entreated of Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall rytes. And I woulde not haue I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous rytes vnpurged of errours, tranſlated into reformed Churches. And
<pb facs="tcp:11542:11"/> agayne, and on the contrarie parte, it might be demaunded, whether receyued Rytes, ſuperſtition being remoued, may not by diſcipline and order be retained without ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Whether conformitie in ceremonies, be of neceſſitie to be exacted? I anſwere, That conformitie in ceremonies is not paraduenture neceſſarie in al Churches. In the meane ſeaſon if a thing not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie be commaunded, ſo that the ſame be not vngodly, it ſeemeth not that therfore the Church ſhoulde be forſaken. There was not conformitie in rytes in all the olde Churches. Yet ſuche as kéept not conformitie, reproued not the kéepers of vniforme rites. And I am eaſely perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that pollitike wiſe men vrge this v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformitie of rytes, bicauſe they thinke it maketh vnto concorde, and bicauſe the Church of al Englande, is one Church, wherein if there be no impietie mixed, I ſée not howe ye can ſo fiercely ſette your ſelues againſte ſuche orders being not euill.</p>
                  <p>Whether Ceremonies openly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue
<pb facs="tcp:11542:12"/> may be retayned? I aunſwere, that offence ought to be auoyded. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane time, we muſt beware that we couer not our owne affections vnder the name of offence. Ye knowe there is an offence giuen, and an offence taken, and as it were ſought of our ſelues. I diſpute not now, whether you can for a thing indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent without giuing of grieuous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, forſake the Churches that Chriſt dyed for.</p>
                  <p>Whether any orders are to be borne in the Church, which in their owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in déede are not vngodlie, but yet make nothing for edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? I anſwere, if the orders which the Quenes maieſtie enioyneth you be voyde of impietie, ye ought rather to beare them than forſake your Churches, for if the edifying of the Church is chiefely to be ſought in this matter, verily we ſhall ſoner deſtroy the Church by forſaking it than by putting on the Apparell. And where vngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is not, neyther the conſcience offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, there muſt we not giue ouer, though we ſhoulde beare ſome ſeruitude. And
<pb facs="tcp:11542:12"/> here agayne it might be demaunded, whether Apparell may iuſtly be compted ſeruitude, ſo farre forth as it ſerueth to comlyneſſe and order.</p>
                  <p>Whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince ought to preſcribe anye thing to the Churches in Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies without the good will and frée con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of eccleſiaſticall perſons. I anſwere, if the Prince ſhoulde alwayes haue ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the good will of his cleargie, parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture the moſte wiſe and godly kings <hi>Ioſaphat, Ezechias, Aſa</hi> and <hi>Ioſias</hi> and other good Princes, had neuer brought the Leuites and Miniſters of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches into order. Albeit my mind is not at all, that Biſhops ſhoulde be ſhut out of conſultations for the Church. Againe I would not haue them chalenge ſuch au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to themſelues as they haue vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped againſt Princes and Magiſtrates in Papacie. Neyther woulde I haue Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to holde their peace and agrée vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vniuſt ordinaunces of Princes.</p>
                  <p>The laſt two queſtions touch the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nearer. Whether it were better in thys order to ſerue the Churche, or
<pb facs="tcp:11542:13"/> for theſe thinges to be caſt out of eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall function? And whether good Paſtors may for the neglecting of ſuche Ceremonies, iuſtly be put from the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie? I anſwere, if there be no ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition nor impietie in the rytes, and yet they are enforced, and enioyned good Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, which had rather be diſcharged of them, in déede I will graunt, and that more liberally than néedeth, that a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and ſeruitude is layde vpon them, but I will not graunt, and that for moſt iuſt cauſes, that therefore they ſhoulde forſake their place or miniſterie, and giue ouer vnto Wolues, as it hath bene ſayd already, or to vnfitter Miniſters, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when libertie to preache is not taken away, and prouiſion may be made that no further ſeruitude creepe in, and many ſuch like things.</p>
                  <p>I haue ſayde what I thought to be ſaide of the matters propounded in queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, knowing that other men for their learning coulde haue better and more finely diſcuſſed them, but bicauſe it was your mindes, that I ſhoulde anſwere,
<pb facs="tcp:11542:13"/> I haue done as I coulde, leauing to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at libertie both pen and iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. To ende, my minde is not with theſe, to force or entangle any mans conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but I offer them to be examined, and I aduiſe, that no man in this controuerſie, frame himſelfe a conſcience, of a deſire to contende. And I exhort you al by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord, the Sauiour, Head, and King of his Churche, that euerye one well weighe with him ſelfe, which way he ſhall more edifie the Church of Chriſt, by putting on the Apparell as a thing indifferent, for order and comely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake, and ſo far ſomewhat making to concorde and profite of the Church, or for Apparell to forſake the Church, and leaue it to be poſſeſſed afterwarde if not of manifeſt Wolues, yet of vnfitter and worſſe Miniſters at the leaſt. The Lord Ieſus graunt you to ſee, ſauour, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that which maketh to his glory, and the ſafetie and peace of his Church. Fare ye well in the Lorde, together with all the faithfull Miniſters. Wée will hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily praye to the Lorde for, you that ye
<pb facs="tcp:11542:14"/> maye thinke and doe, that is holye and holeſome. <hi>D. Gualter</hi> hath him moſte heartily commended vnto you, &amp; wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you all proſperitie. And ſo doe the reſt of the Miniſters alſo.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>At <hi>Zurich</hi> 
                        <date>the firſt day of Maij In the yeare of our Lorde. 1566.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Henry Bullinger, Miniſter of the Church of Zurich: in his owne, and Gualters name.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by</hi> William Seres, dwelling <hi>in Paules Church yarde, at</hi> the Signe of the <hi>Hedgehogge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:14"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="lat">
            <front>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:15"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Reuerendis in Chriſto Patribus D. Roberto Horno Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> D. Grindallo Londonien. &amp; D. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curstho Noruicen. Epiſcopis in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia, Dominis nostris colendiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, &amp; fratribus cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsimis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EVERENDI VIRI, Domini honorandi, &amp; fratres chariſsimi. Dominus Ieſus benedicat vobis &amp; ſeruet ab omni malo. Mittimus ſcriptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nostrum de re vestiaria da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum à nobis ad N. &amp; M. viros doctos &amp; pios, fratres nostros colendos. Ideo autem mittimus ad vos, vt intelligatis, inſcijs vobis primarijs ministris, nihil nos priuatim agere cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fratri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; quod per omnia pacem eccleſiarum veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarum, quantum quidem poſsumus, quaerimus. Oramus quoquè dominum, vt rebus vestris ſemper conſulat, &amp; vos ſeruet in concordia. Vos hortamur viri reuerendi, &amp; fratres chariſs. ri rationem habeatis fidelium ministrorum, &amp; doctorum hominum, habent hi ſerè ſuas affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones: vnde Apostolus quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> monuit, vt alij
<pb facs="tcp:11542:16"/> aliorum onera portent. Veſtra authoritate pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum potestis apud ſereniſs. D. Reginam, apud eius maiestatem efficite, vt boni fratres recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilientur et restituantur. Rogamus item vt tu D. Horne obſeruande domine, &amp; frater chariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime, cui primum hae literae dari poſsunt, ilico cures eas perferri ad D. Noruicenſem, eaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes habeatis cum D. Iuello, D. Sando, &amp; D. Pilchinthono, quibus proximis nundinis Frankford. deo volente ſcribam. Has festina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsime exaraui, tam meo, quam Gualtheri no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, &amp; Baſileam miſimus inde tranſportan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Antuerpiam. Vos ſedulo oramus, vt ſignificetis, an receperitis. Optime valete viri reuerendi. Dominus benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat vobis &amp; vestris labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Tiguri. <date>
                           <hi>3.</hi> Maij. <hi>1566.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Bullingerus vester.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:16"/>
                  <head>Dominis N. et M.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>OMINVS</hi> IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus benedicat vobis, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ornatiſsimi &amp; fratres chariſsimi, ac ſeruet vos ab omni malo. Accepi literas vestras, ex qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus intellexite. N. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queri, quod mea reſponſio data ad tuam quaeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, nimis videatur acciſa. Ego vero, mi fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, tunc non vidi, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nunc video quorſum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuerit copioſiores ſcribere literas. Nam ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabas tu duntaxat, quae eſset mea de re vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aria, de qua contendebatur in Anglia, ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. Ad hanc quaestionem breuibus tibi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondendum putaui. Nam breuibus meam ſententia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dicere potui. Dein ſciebam beatae me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriae D. Pet. Martyrem &amp; Oxoniae &amp; hic, eandem quaeſtionem tractauiſse ſaepius &amp; fuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, quibus quod adi cerem non habebam. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini vero in literis ad te. M. fratrem daias, meae quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſententiae factam tunc quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fuiſse mentionem. Et vt iterum vno &amp; altero verbo quod ſentio dicam: Nun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> probauerim ſi iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beamini veſtrum exequi ministerium. ad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram crucifixi imagine oneratam magis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natam,
<pb facs="tcp:11542:17"/> &amp; in veste Miſsatica, hoc est, in alba &amp; Caſula, quae à tergo quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ostentet crucifixi imaginem. At quantum ex literis ex Anglia allatis intellego, nulla nunc eſt de eiuſmodi veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te contentio: Sed questio est: An liceat Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris Euangelicis portare pileum rotundum vel quadratum, &amp; vestem albam, quam nuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant ſuperpellicium, qua minister ornatus, à vulgo diſcernatur? Et an oporteat ministeriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vel ſtationem ſacra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> citius relinquere, q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> huiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi veſtibus vti? Reſpondi ad hanc quaesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem preteritis nundinis Reuerendo viro Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Roberto Horno Winton. Epiſcopo, &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breuibus repetens verba D. Martyris. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerat eide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paulo ante Symmista, &amp; affinis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us chariſsimus D. Rodolphus Gualtherus, cuius exemplum hiſce incluſum ad vos &amp; ad alios fratres nostros, mitto. Ergo ſi nos audire vultis, noſtrumque iudicium de re vestiaria expetitis, ſicut vltimis vestris ad me literis ſignificaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, en habetis in illa Epiſtola noſtrum iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, cui ſi acquieſcere non potestis, dolemus ſanc qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vehementiſsime, &amp; cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nullum nobis ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſuperſit conſilium, Dominum, qui in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; ſemper reſpiciendus eſt, ex animo &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsanter oramus, vt ipſe gratia ſua at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> potentia
<pb facs="tcp:11542:17"/> rebus afflictis conſulat.</p>
                  <p>Quaestiones aliquot tu N. frater propoſuiſti plures vero eiuſdem argumenti M. noster con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texuit. Licet vero pro mea ſimplici ruditate, nun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> probauerim res in tot distrahi quaeſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; nodis innecti implicatioribus quaealio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui ſimpliciores per ſe, breuibus &amp; ſatis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicue expediri potuerant, aliquid tamen anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabo ad ſingulas, vt hac quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in re, vobis Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis meis obſeruandis &amp; fratribus chariſsimis, quantum per meam poſsum infantiam acumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>què retuſum magis q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acutum, inſerutam. Vos autem oro vt benigne haec à me fratre vestro vestri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> amantiſsimo accipiatis, &amp; de his animo iudicetis ab affectibus purgato at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tranquillo. A contentionibus abhorreo prorſus, &amp; nihil magis ſupplex peto a domino, quam vt ab eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia longe remoueat contentiones, quae ab initio &amp; ſemper plurimum nocuere vera pietati, &amp; eccleſiam vtcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pacatam &amp; ſtorentem, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerarunt.</p>
                  <p>Cum quaeritur an debeant eccleſiasticis leges praeſcribi vestiariae, vt ijs distinguantu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>à laicis. Respondeo, Ambiguitatem eſse in verbo <hi>Debere.</hi> Si enim accipiatur pro neceſsario, &amp; quod ad ſalutem conſequendam pertineat, non
<pb facs="tcp:11542:18"/> arbitror hoc velle vel ipſos legum authores. Si vero dicatur poſse hoc fieri decoris ornatuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, vel dignitatis &amp; ordinis gratia, vt ſit ciuilis quaeda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſeruatio, aut tale quid intelligatur quale illud eſt quod Apoſtolus vult miniſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vel Epiſcopu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiae, <hi>Coſmion,</hi> compoſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vel orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſse, non video quid peccet qui veſte huiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi vtit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, aut qui eiuſmodi veſte vti iubet</p>
                  <p>An ceremonialis cultus Leuitici ſacerdotij ſit reuocandus in eccleſiam? Reſpondeo, Si pileus &amp; vestis non indecora miniſtro, &amp; quae ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitione carent, iubeantur vſurpari à mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris nemo ſane dixerit verè Iudaiſmum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocari. Praeterea repeto hic quod ad hanc quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionem video reſpondiſse D. Martyrem, qui vbi ostendiſset ſacramenta veteris legis eſse abolita quae non oporteat reducere in eccleſiam Christi, quae habeat baptiſmum &amp; ſacra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coenam, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecit: Fuerunt nihilominus in lege Leuitica ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones aliquae ita comparatae, vt propriè ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta dici non poſsent. Faciebant enim ad decorem &amp; ordinem &amp; aliquam commoditatem, quae vt lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini naturae congrua, &amp; ad nostram aliquam vtilitatem conducentia, ego &amp; reuocari &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineri poſse iudico. Quis non videt Apostolos pro pace &amp; conuictu credentium faciliori, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſse
<pb facs="tcp:11542:18"/> gentibus vt à ſanguine &amp; praſocato ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinerent? Erant haec citra controuerſiam lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia &amp; Leuitica. Decimas quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hodie multis in locis inſtitutas eſse ad alendos miniſtros nemo nostrum ignorat. Pſalmos &amp; Hymnos cant in ſacris coetibus manifeſtum eſt, quod tamen Leuitae quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vſurparunt. Vt<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hoc non omittá, Dies habemus feſtos in memoriam Dominica reſurrectionis, &amp; alia. An vero illa omnia erunt abolenda, quia ſunt veſtigia legis anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae? Vides ergo non omnia Leuitica ſic eſse antiquata, vt quaedam exijs vſurpart non paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſint. Haec ille. An vestitu cum papiſtis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municare liceat. Reſpondeo, non dum constar Papam diſcrimen veſtium induxiſse in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. Imo diſcrimen vestium conſtat eſſe Papa longe vetustius. Nec viden cur non liceat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitu non ſuperstitioſo, ſed politico &amp; compoſito communicare cum papistis. Si nulla re cum illis communicare liceret, oporteret &amp; templa omnia deſerere, nulla accipere ſtipendia, non vta baptiſmo, non recitare ſymbolum Apostolorum &amp; Nicenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, adeo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> abijcere orationem domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam. Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vos mutuatas ab ris vllas ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as. Res vestiaria ab initio reformationis nun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fuit abolita, &amp; retinetur adhuc non lege papiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,
<pb facs="tcp:11542:19"/> ſed vi edicti Regij, vt res media &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litica.</p>
                  <p>Ita ſane, ſi vt re ciuili vt amini pileo &amp; veste peculiari, non hoc redolet Iudaiſmum ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachiſmum. Nam hi volunt videri a ciuili vita ſeparati, &amp; conſtituunt meritum in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiari ſua veſte. Sic Eustachius. Sebaſtiae Epiſcopus damnatus eſt, non ſimpliciter propter peculiarem veſtem, ſed quod in veste religionem constitueret. Noti ſunt Gaugreu. Concilij ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nones, Laodiceni, &amp; VI. Synod. Quod ſi ex plebe nonnulli ſunt perſuaſi redolere hoc papiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, Iudaiſmum &amp; Monachiſmum, admone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur, &amp; recte de his instituantur. Quod ſi importunis quorundam clamoribus hac de re ad vulgus profuſis, multi inquieti redduntur, videant qui hoc faciunt, ne grauiora ſibi oner a imponant, Regiam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Maieſtatem irritent, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> multos fideles Ministros in diſcrimen ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducant, ex quo vix emergere queant.</p>
                  <p>An qui libertate ſua hactenus acquieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, vt edicti Regij, hac ſeruitute implicare &amp; ſé &amp; eccleſiam, ſalua conſcientia poſsint? Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondeo, Cauendum ego cenſeo ne odioſius diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putetur, clametur, &amp; contendatur de re vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aria, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> importunitate hac detur occaſio Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae
<pb facs="tcp:11542:19"/> Maiestati, vt liberu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amplius illis no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quat, qui libertate hactenús vſi ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſed clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus neceſsarijs irritata, mandet vel ſumere veſtes illas eccleſiasticas, vel cedere ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſua, Miru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſane mihi videtur (veſtra pace viri orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimi, &amp; fratres chariſsimi dixerim) quod vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis perſuadetis, ſalua conſcientia vos &amp; eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſeruituti vestiariae ſubijcere non poſse, &amp; non potius expenditis, ſi re politica &amp; indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti vti nolitis, &amp; perpetuo cotendatis odioſius, cui uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi ſcruituti &amp; vos &amp; eccleſias ſubijciatis, qui veſtra ſtatione cede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, lupis exponitis eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, aut ſaltem paru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> idoneis doctoribus, qui non aequè vt vos ad docendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> populum ſunt instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. An vero eccleſias in libertatem aſseruiſtis, quando occaſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuppeditatis, eccleſiam pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus grauioribuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> oneribus opprimendi? Non ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noratis quid multi quaerant, quomodo erga E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelij predicatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſint affecti, &amp; quales vobis ſucceſſuri ſint, &amp; quid de illis ſperandum ſit.</p>
                  <p>An vestitus clericalis ſit res indifferens? Videtur ſane res indifferens cum ſit res ciuilis, ac decori, ornatus, ordiniſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> habeat rationem in qua cultus non constituitur. Haec breuibus ad tuas volui reſpondere Doctiſsime &amp; dilectiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, mi Frater N.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:21"/>
                  <p>Iam venio &amp; ad M. nostri quaeſtiones, in quibus exponendis ero fortaſse breuior. An vestitus peculiaris à laicis distinctus, ministris eccleſiae nun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fuerit constitutus? an &amp; hodie in reformata eccleſia debeat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stitui? Reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deo, in veteri eccleſia fuiſse peculiarem presbytero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vestitum apparet ex hiſtoria eccleſiastica Thedoreti lib. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>27.</hi> &amp; Socratis lib. <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>22.</hi> pallio in ſacris vſos eſſe ministros, nemo ignorat qui veterum monumenta obiter inſpexit. Ideo antea ſubmonui diuerſitatem indumentorum non habere ſuam originem à papa. Euſebius cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te testatur ex vetustiſsimis ſcriptoribus Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannem Apostolum Epheſi petalum ſeu lami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam geſtaſse pontificalem in capite. Et de Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priano martyre testatur Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius Diaconus quod cum iugulum carnifici praebere vellet ei prius birrum dediſse, diacono vero dalmaticam, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſic ipſum in lineis ſtetiſse indutum. Praeterea vestis candidae miniſtrorum meminit Chriſoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. At certum est Christianos cum a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſmo conuerterentur ad Euangelium &amp; ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam, pro toga induiſse pallium: Ob quam rem cum ab infidelibus irriderentur, Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus librum de pallio ſcripſit cruditiſsimum. Alia huius generis plura proferre poſsem, niſi
<pb facs="tcp:11542:21"/> haec ſufficerent. Mallem quidem nihil inuitis inijci ministris, &amp; eos ea vti poſse conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, qua Apostoli. Sed quando Regia Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestas pileum tantummodo &amp; candidam veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inijcit, in qua cultum (quod ſaepe iam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitum eſt) non constituit, eadem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> res apud veteres, dum meliores adhuc eccleſiae res eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, vſurpatae ſunt abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuperstitione &amp; cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae, optarem bonos ministros in his, non vt in prora &amp; puppi, quod dicitur, totum constituere Religionis profectum, ſed dare aliquid tempori &amp; de re indifferenti non odioſius altercari, ſed modeſte iudicare, haec quidem fieri poſse, ſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiendum cum tempore. Propiores enim eſse A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicae ſimplicitati, qui diſcrimina illa igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, aut non vrgeant, interim tamen à diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na in amictu non ſunt alieni.</p>
                  <p>An vestium praeſcriptio congruat &amp; Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiana libertate? Reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deo, Res indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere aliquando perſcripti nem adeo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> coacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, vt ſic dicam quo ad vſum, &amp; non quo ad neceſsitatem, vt aliquid ſcilicet quod natura ſit indifferens, vt neceſsarium conſcientiae ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudatur, &amp; ita animis inijciatur religio. Tempora certe &amp; loca ſacrorum coetuum recte habentur inter indifferentia, &amp; tamen ſi hic
<pb facs="tcp:11542:22"/> nulla ſit praeſcriptio, quanta obſecro confuſio co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbatio<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> orietur?</p>
                  <p>An vllae ceremoniae nouae praeter expreſsum praeſcriptum verbi Dei cumulari poſsint? Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondeo, me non probare ſi nouae cumulentur ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniae: ſed tamen aliquas institui poſse non negarim, modo in eis non ſtatuatur dei cultus, ſed instituantur propter ordinem &amp; diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Christus ipſe Encaeniorum feſtum vel cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniam ſeruauit, nec tamen lege praeſcriptum legimus hoc festum. In ſumma, propoſitionum vel quaeſtionum de re vestiaria potior pars de eo diſputat, An de vestibus leges in eccleſia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di vel debeant vel poſsint? Ac quaeſtionem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocat ad genus, quidnam videlicet de ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nijs ſtatucre liceat? Ad has propoſitiones pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deo, me quidem malle nullas ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as niſi neceſsarias obtrudi eccleſiae, interim tamen fateor non poſſe ſtatim leges de his, forte non adeo neceſsarias, aliquando &amp; inutiles, damnari impietatis, turbaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; ſchiſma exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare in eccleſia, quum videlicet ſuperſtitione ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent &amp; res ſunt ſua natura indifferentes.</p>
                  <p>An ritus Iudaeorum antiquatos renouare, religioni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Idololatrarum proprie dicatos, in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus reformatarum eccleſiarum liceat transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re?
<pb facs="tcp:11542:22"/> De haec quaeſtione antea reſpondi, vbi diſse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rui de Leuiticis ritibus. Nolim vero ritus Idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latricos no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repurgatos ab erroribus transferri in eccleſias reformatas. Rurſus vero &amp; ex aduerſo quaeri poterat, an recepti ritus, remota ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, propter diſciplinam &amp; ordinem retineri ſiue peccato non poſsint?</p>
                  <p>An conformatio in ceremonijs neceſsario ſit exigenda? Reſpondeo, Conformationem in cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monijs in omnibus eccleſijs ſorte non eſſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariam. Interim ſi praecipiatur res non neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, rurſus tamen non impia, ob eam, eccleſia non videtur eſſe deſerenda. Non fuit in ritibus conformitas in omnibus eccleſijs vetuſtioribus. Quae tamen conformibus vtebantur ritibus, eas non vituperabant conformitate carentes: facile autem credo viros prudentes at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> politicos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formationem rituum vrgere, quod exiſtiment hanc facere ad concordiam, &amp; quod vna ſit eccleſia totius Angliae: In quare ſi nihil im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pij miſceatur, non video quomodo eiuſmodi non malis inſtitutis, hoſtiliter vos obijciatis.</p>
                  <p>An ceremoniae cum aperto ſcandalo coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae retineri poſsint? Reſpondeo, ſcandalum vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri oportere. Videndum interim ne ſub ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo nostras affectiones contegamus. Non ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis
<pb facs="tcp:11542:23"/> aliud quidem datum, aliud vero acceptum &amp; vltro accerſitum eſse ſcandalum. Non diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puto nunc an vos ſinc graui ſcandalo dato deſc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere poſsitis eccleſias, pro quibus Chriſtus mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus eſt, propter rem indifferentem.</p>
                  <p>An vllae conſtitutiones ferendae in eccleſia, quae natura ſua impiae quidem non ſunt, ſed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ad aedificationem nihil faciunt? Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo, ſi conſtitutiones impietate carent, quas vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis imponere vult Regiae Maiestas, ferendae ſunt potius <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> deſerendae eccleſiae. Si enim aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatio eccleſiae hac in re potiſsimum eſt ſpectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, deſerendo certè eccleſiam plus deſtruxerimus eccleſiam, quam veſtes induendo. Et vbi abeſt impietas, nec laeditur conſcientia, ibi cedendum non eſt, licet aliqua imponatur ſeruitus. Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim vero quaerirur ſus poterat an ſub ſeruitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem iuſte referamus rem veſtiariam, quatenus facit ad decorem &amp; ordinem.</p>
                  <p>An quic<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eccleſijs à principe praeſcribendum in Ceremonijs ſine voluntate &amp; libero conſenſu Eccleſiaſticorum? Reſpondeo, Si voluntas Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticorum ſemper ſit expectanda principi, nun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> forte ſapientiſsimi &amp; pijſsimi Reges Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat, Ezechias, Aſa, &amp; Ioſias, alij<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes boni, leuitas &amp; miniſtros eccleſiarum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degiſſent
<pb facs="tcp:11542:23"/> in ordinem. Quamuis nolim prorſus excludi Epſcopos a conſultationibus eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. Nolim rurſus eos eam ſibi potentiam vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, quam ſibi vſurparunt contra principes &amp; magiſtratus in papatu. Nolimitem tacere Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copos &amp; conſentire ad iniqua principu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſtituta.</p>
                  <p>Poſtremae quaeſtiones duae propius ad rem ipſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accedu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, An conſultius ſiteccleſiae ſic inſeruire, an propterea eccleſiaſtico munere eijci? Et, an boni paſtores iure ob huiuſmodi ceremonias neg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lectas à miniſterio amoueri poſsint? Reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deo, ſi in ritibus nulla eſt ſuperſtitio, nulla impietas, vrgentur tamen, &amp; imponu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur bonis paſtoribus qui mallent illos ſibi non imponi, dabo ſane, &amp; quidem ex abundanti, onus &amp; ſeruitutem ipſis imponi, ſed non dabo, id<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iuſtiſsimis ex cauſis, ſtationem vel miniſterium propterea eſse deſere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; locum cedendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lupis, vt antea dictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, vel ineptioribus miniſtris, preſertim cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maneat libera predicatio, caueri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> poſsit ne maior obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur ſcruitus, &amp; multa huius generis alia.</p>
                  <p>Dixi quae mihi videbantur dicenda de propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitis quaestionibus, non neſcius alios pro ſua e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruditione longe elegantius meliuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> potuiſse ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſsiſse, ſed quia ita voluistis vt reſponderem, feci quod potui, liberum alijs relinquens de his
<pb facs="tcp:11542:24"/> &amp; calamum &amp; iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Quod ſupereſt, nullius ego his conſcientiam vrgere &amp; irretire volos ſed examinanda propono, moneo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ne quis in hac co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſia ex co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentionis ſtudio ſibi faciat conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Hortor item vos omnes per Ieſum Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m nostru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Eccleſiae ſuae ſeruatorem, caput &amp; Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt probe quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> apud ſe expendat, vera nam re plus aedificarit eccleſia Chriſti, ſi propter ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; decore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veſtibus vt atur, vt re indifferenti, &amp; hactenus ad concordia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtilitatem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eccleſiae nonnihil faciente, an vero propter rem veſti aria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſerat eccleſiam, occupandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſtea ſi non a lupis manifeſtis, ſalte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a miniſtris minime idontia &amp; bonis, Dominus Ieſus det vobis videre, ſapere, &amp; ſequi quod facit ad gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius, &amp; eccleſiae pacem &amp; ſalutem. Valete in domino vna cum omnibus fidelibus ministris. Orabimus ſedulo pro vobis dominum, vt ea ſentiatis &amp; faciatis, quae ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cta ſunt &amp; ſalutaria. D. Gualthcrus amiciſsime vos ſalutat, &amp; omnia foelicia vobis precatur, faciunt hoc ipſum reliqui etiam ministri.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guri <date>Calend. Maij Anno Domini. 1566.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Henricus Bullingerus Tigurinae Eccleſiae minister, ſuo, &amp; Gualtheri nomine.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>EXCVSVM LONDINI APVD Guillihelmum Seres. Anno. 1566.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11542:24"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
